Manulife Financial Corporation is a Canadian
insurance company and financial services provider,
with a head office in Toronto, Canada.
The company operates in Canada and Asia as
"Manulife Financial" and in the United States
primarily through its John Hancock division.
It is one of the largest life insurance companies
in the world by market capitalization, and
has approximately 84,000 employees.
Manulife Bank of Canada is a wholly owned
subsidiary of Manulife Financial Corporation.
History
Private stock company
The firm was founded as The Manufacturers
Life Insurance Company in 1887.
Its first president was Sir John A. Macdonald,
the first Prime Minister of Canada.
The company sold its first policy outside
of Canada in Bermuda in 1893.
In 1894, policies were sold in Grenada, Jamaica
and Barbados; Trinidad and Tobago, and Haiti
in 1895; and British Honduras, British Guiana,
China and Hong Kong in 1897.
In 1901, Manulife amalgamated with the Temperance
and General Life Assurance Company, a Toronto-based
Canadian life insurer that provided preferred
rates to abstainers of alcohol.
Manulife continued to offer abstainers rates
into the 1920s.
In 1931, it opened its first southern China
branch in British Hong Kong.
Shortly thereafter, it established itself
as a leading life insurer in the region with
branches in Macau, Shantou and Amoy.
Mutual company
In 1958, shareholders voted to change its
legal form from a joint stock company to a
mutual organization, making the company privately
owned by its policyholders.
In 1996, the company entered an agreement
with the Zhong Hong Life Insurance Co. Ltd.,
based in Shanghai, to form China’s first
joint venture life insurance company, Manulife-Sinochem.
In 1984, Manulife announced that it had acquired
Waterloo, Ontario-based Dominion Life Assurance
Company: a deal that included the purchase
of all of the outstanding stock of the company
from Lincoln National.
Dominion Life was founded in Waterloo in 1889,
and Manulife made a commitment to the community
to retain a significant presence in Waterloo.
In 1988, Manulife opened a new five-storey
office building at 500 King St. North in Waterloo
to house its Canadian Division.
In 1996, the company entered an agreement
with Sinochem to form Shanghai -based Zhong
Hong Life Insurance Co. Ltd., China’s first
joint venture life insurance company, and
was granted a license that made it the second
foreign insurer to be allowed re-entry into
China.
Demutualization and public company
In 1999, its voting eligible policyholders
approved demutualization, and the shares of
Manulife Financial Corporation, the holding
company of The Manufacturers Life Insurance
Company and its subsidiaries, began trading
on The Toronto Stock Exchange, the New York
Stock Exchange and the Philippine Stock Exchange
under the ticker 'MFC', and on The Stock Exchange
of Hong Kong under the ticker ‘945’.
In 2002, Manulife–Sinochem Life Insurance
Co. Ltd. was granted approval by the China
Insurance Regulatory Commission to open a
branch office in Guangzhou, China, the first
branch license granted to a foreign invested
joint–venture life insurance company.
In 2003, Manulife-Sinochem received approval
for a branch office in Beijing, the first
multiple-branch license granted to a foreign-invested
joint venture life insurance company.
The firm is now licensed to operate in more
than 50 Chinese cities.
In 2003, Manulife Financial Corporation and
John Hancock Financial Services, Inc. announced
a tax–free stock–for–stock merger of
the companies, creating a global insurance
franchise.
Completed in April 2004, the merger created
the largest life insurer in Canada, second
largest in North America, and fifth largest
in the world at the time.
In 2013 Richard DeWolfe became the Chair of
the company’s board, succeeding Gail Cook-Bennett,
who retired after serving 34 years on the
board.
In 2009, Donald Guloien, the Chief Investment
Officer, succeeded Dominic D’Alessandro
as President and CEO of the company.
Shortly before his departure, D’Alessandro
modified his retirement package; the restricted
units would only vest for a total of $10 million
if the shares reached $36 by the end of 2011,
and he would receive $5 million if the shares
hit $30.
This was in response to shareholders’ reaction
to the first quarterly loss ever posted by
the firm in its public history.
Under Guloien's leadership, the first initiatives
were a dividend cut and an equity offering
to bolster Manulife's capital levels, making
it difficult for the share price to reach
the target levels needed to vest.
In September 2009, the company purchased AIC’s
Canadian retail investment fund business.
In October 2009, it purchased Pottruff & Smith
Travel Insurance Brokers Inc., a Canadian
broker and third party administrator of travel
insurance.
In 2010, the company announced that it had
purchased Fortis Bank SA/NV’s1 49 per cent
ownership in ABN AMRO TEDA Fund Management
Co. Ltd.
The new joint venture, Manulife TEDA Fund
Management Company Ltd., provides traditional
retail and institutional asset management
for clients in China.
The other 51 per cent is owned by Northern
International Trust, part of Tianjin TEDA
Investment Holding Co., Ltd..
In June 2012, the company opened Manulife
Cambodia, with headquarters in Phnom Penh.
In September 2014, Manulife agreed to acquire
the Canadian operations of Standard Life for
a fee of around $3.7 billion.
Awards
2013 and 2014 – named to the Dow Jones Sustainability
North American Index
2013 – The Manulife LPGA Classic received
the Tournament Owners Association Gold Driver
Award for Charity Promotion, with St. Mary’s
General Hospital Foundation’s Red Day
2012 and 2013 – named one of Canada’s
Top Employers for Young People
2010 through 2013 – named one of Canada’s
Top 100 Employers
2012 – Manulife Investments received the
Order of Excellence Award from Excellence
Canada
2012 – President and CEO Donald Guloien
named 2012 International Business Executive
of the Year
2010 – Manulife Financial recognized on
the 2010 Investor 500 ranking by Canadian
Business magazine
2010 – Manulife-Sinochem received an award
of excellence from the State Council National
Economic Census Commission
Sponsorship
Manulife Financial was worldwide sponsor for
the 2008 Summer Olympics.
The sponsorship was acquired along with John
Hancock Financial Services.
Manulife is the namesake tenant in the tallest
building in Edmonton, Alberta, Manulife Place.
In 2010, Manulife partnered with Volunteer
Canada and launched its “Get Volunteering”
platform to provide Canadians with tools to
find volunteer experiences, officially adopting
volunteerism as the signature cause of its
corporate social investment program.
Title sponsor of the Manulife Financial LPGA
Classic since 2012.
Manulife is the parent company of John Hancock
Financial, which has been a principal sponsor
of the Boston Marathon since 1986.
Sponsor of Pathways To Education Canada, a
program focused on reducing high school dropout
rates in low-income communities.
Manulife Japan is a sponsor of Hoshi General
Hospital’s “Manulife Waku Waku Room”
project, providing psychological support for
children receiving medical care.
Title sponsor of the Manulife Walk for Memories,
benefitting the Alzheimer Society of Toronto.
References
External links
Manulife Financial Corporate website
Manulife Financial Corporation at The Canadian
Encyclopedia